A Guide to the Papers of the Anderson Family 1771-1952
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the Anderson Family 1771-1952
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
38-96
These files constitute a large volume of personal, legal and business correspondence, legal and financial papers, ledgers and daybooks, ca. 7,000 items (41 boxes, ca. 17 linear feet).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The Anderson Family papers were loaned to the University of Virginia Library by Miss Ellen G. Anderson, Lexington, Virginia, in 1931 and 1934.
Biographical/Historical Information
Francis Thomas Anderson (1808-1887) was a lawyer, legislator, Rector of Washington and Lee University (1879-1887) and Judge of the Supreme Court of Appeals of Virginia. He was born at Walnut Hill in Botetourt County, Virginia, to William Anderson and Anna Thomas Anderson, one of ten children. Francis Anderson graduated from Washington College in 1827, read law with Fleming B. Miller and Allen Taylor, and was admitted to the bar in 1830. He was married to Mary Ann Alexander Anderson on December 8, 1830 and they had nine children. In 1856, they moved to Rockbridge County, Virginia, where he operated a large iron foundry at Glenwood for twelve years. Anderson belonged to the Whig Party, opposing secession until after the firing on Fort Sumter. He represented Rockbridge County in the House of Delegates from December 1861 until March 1863. He resumed his law practice in Lexington, Virginia, in 1869.
His brothers, John Thomas Anderson and Joseph Reid Anderson, were both prominent politicians and iron manufacturers. Joseph Reid Anderson took charge of the Tredegar Ironworks, Richmond, Virginia in 1841, eventually purchasing Tredegar on April 4, 1848, for $125,000. After the incident with John Brown at Harper's Ferry, Tredegar got the bid for equipping the Richmond State Armory and became very important to the Confederacy during the Civil War. Tredegar continued to produce munitions during two world wars and became the oldest surviving iron works south of the Potomac River.
William Alexander Anderson (1842-1930) was a lawyer and politician, Attorney General of Virginia, and Rector of Washington and Lee University, 1914-1923, and member of its Board of Trustees from 1884 until his death. Anderson was the son of Judge Francis T. Anderson and Mary Ann Alexander Anderson.
While a student at Washington College (now Washington and Lee University), William Anderson served in the Liberty Hall Volunteers as an orderly sergeant during the beginning of the Civil War, April 1861. He was seriously wounded at First Manassas on July 21, 1861, as part of the Stonewall Brigade, Company I, 4th Virginia Infantry. After being discharged, he entered the University of Virginia in 1863 and received his law degree in 1866. His first wife was Ellen Graham Anderson, of Richmond, who died in January 1872. After her death, he married Mary Louisa ("Maza") Blair, Lexington, on August 9, 1975, and they had five children.
He became a lawyer in Rockbridge County, Virginia, in 1867, and was nominated and elected state senator from the Rockbridge-Botetourt district, 1869-1873. In 1870, Anderson was credited with introducing the bill establishing the public school system of Virginia as put forth by Dr. William Henry Ruffner. He also served in the House of Delegates for three terms and was a member of the Virginia Constitutional Convention, 1901-1902, becoming the first attorney general under Virginia's new constitution, 1902-1910. Other types of service include his work as a member of the state Democratic executive committee for six years, as one of the United States commissioners to the Paris International Exposition in 1878, and his election as president of the Virginia Bar Association in 1899.
Scope and Content
These files constitute a large volume of personal, legal and business correspondence, legal and financial papers, ledgers and daybooks, ca. 7,000 items (41 boxes, ca. 17 linear feet), 1771 to 1952, primarily from the legal careers of Francis Thomas Anderson (1808-1887) and William Alexander Anderson (1842-1930) of Lexington and Rockbridge County, Virginia. The papers are largely comprised of documents concerning coal, tin, iron and agricultural lands in Virginia and West Virginia as well as the activities of major iron companies, including the Tredegar Company in Richmond.
There are also numerous court cases including the Virginia-West Virginia debt controversy. As attorney general of Virginia, William A. Anderson prepared the briefs and arguments in the famous debt controversy case, which ultimately reached the United States Supreme Court.
Some letters of note include: a letter from Socrates Maupin from the University of Virginia discussing the number of students attending, and the professor of law, John A.G. Davis (October 10, 1830); a resolution written on the back of a letter, December 4, 1832, disapproving of South Carolina's nullification of the tariff; letter from the Virginia Military Institute academic board praising Robert Lewis Madison (1828-1878) upon his death (May 27, 1878); an "In Memoriam" for Mary Anne Alexander Anderson, wife of Judge Francis T. Anderson, containing some biographical data (November 30, 1881); Governor Fitzhugh Lee writing about the business of Rockbridge Company (1890 Fall); Governor William Hodges Mann to Samuel W. Williams about retaining William A. Anderson to argue the Richmond, Fredericksburg & Potomac Railroad Case (November 4, 1910); and undated social letters from Thomas Nelson Page.
Also present is a twenty-five page document by William A. Anderson with historical facts about the Arlington Case and the passing of the Arlington Estate from the Lee family (with correspondence in 1920).
Arrangement
The papers are organized in two series: Series I, the papers of the Anderson family; and Series II, Anderson family ledgers. The files are organized alphabetically by subject and in chronological order within their respective subjects.
Separated Material
Printed material concerning the Virginia-West Virginia debt case has been removed and cataloged separately.
Contents List
- Series I: Papers of the Anderson Family (Box 1-41)
  - Correspondence: Letters to Thomas Cross, Primarily from Thomas Tousey 1826-1835 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: Francis T. Anderson 1829-1838, 6 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence: Francis T. Anderson 1839-1844, 6 folders (Box 2)
  - Correspondence: Francis T. Anderson 1845-1856, 7 folders (Box 3)
  - Correspondence: Francis T. Anderson 1856-1868, 8 folders (Box 4)
  - Correspondence: Francis T. Anderson 1869-1874, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Correspondence: Francis T. Anderson and William A. Anderson 1875-1880, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Correspondence: Francis T. Anderson and William A. Anderson 1881-1884, 7 folders (Box 6)
  - Correspondence: Francis T. Anderson and William A. Anderson 1884-1885, 4 folders (Box 7)
  - Correspondence: William A. Anderson 1886-1887, 4 folders (Box 7)
  - Correspondence: William A. Anderson 1887-1891, 7 folders (Box 8)
  - Correspondence: William A. Anderson 1892-1899, 7 folders (Box 9)
  - Correspondence: William A. Anderson 1899-1904, 8 folders (Box 10)
  - Correspondence: William A. Anderson 1905-1913, 7 folders (Box 11)
  - Correspondence: William A. Anderson 1914-1917, 7 folders (Box 12)
  - Correspondence: William A. Anderson 1918-1930, n.d., 8 folders (Box 13)
  - Correspondence: David F. Houston 1919 (Box 13)
  - Correspondence: Lee-Jackson Veterans Camp 1921-1924 (Box 13)
  - Correspondence: Katherine Nuckols to United Daughters of the Confederacy 1951 (Box 13)
  - Haloid Process of Ore Separation 1910 (Box 14)
  - Legal and Financial Papers of Francis T. Anderson 1785-1852, 8 folders (Box 14)
  - Legal and Financial Papers of Francis T. Anderson 1852-1871, 7 folders (Box 15)
  - Legal and Financial Papers of Francis T. Anderson 1872-1879 (Box 16)
  - Legal and Financial Papers of Francis T. Anderson and William A. Anderson 1875-1885, 5 folders (Box 16)
  - Legal and Financial Papers of William A. Anderson 1886-1890, 6 folders (Box 17)
  - Legal and Financial Papers of William A. Anderson 1891-1898, 7 folders (Box 18)
  - Legal and Financial Papers of William A. Anderson 1899-1905, 7 folders (Box 19)
  - Legal and Financial Papers of William A. Anderson 1907-1930, 7 folders (Box 20)
  - Legal and Financial Papers of Francis T. Anderson and William A. Anderson n.d., 2 folders (Box 20)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: Lecture: 40th Freehold Estates 1866 (Box 21)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: Estate of Francis T. Anderson 1880-1909 (Box 21)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: Estate of Francis T. Anderson 1910-1919, n.d. (Box 22)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: Estate of Francis T. Anderson - Miscellaneous Checks and Receipts 1884-1923 (Box 22)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: Receipts of Judith Anderson 1927-1929 (Box 22)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: Bank of Lexington v. C.W. Irvine and Company 1890's, 2 folders (Box 23)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: J.E. and J.C. Cash 1888-1902 (Box 23)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: Estate of Caleb Cushing 1880-1882 (Box 23)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: Dover Iron Company 1866-1874, n.d. (Box 23)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: G.T. Dunlop 1884-1889, 2 folders (Box 23)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: Indenture between William Fenwick and his wife of Richmond, Virginia, and Thomas Cumpston of Philadelphia 1802 Sep. 25 (Box 23)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: Good Road Movement in Virginia 1919-1923 (Box 23)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: Goshen Car and Railway Equipment Company 1891 (Box 24)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: John H. Heald and Company 1899-1901 (Box 24)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: Lady v. Lady 1869-1880 (Box 24)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: Land Grant to John Greenlee signed by Governor Patrick Henry 1786 Jun. 26 (Box 24)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: Land Grant to William Fenwick signed by Governor Robert Brooke 1795 Aug. 20 (Oversize Oversize)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: Mr. and Mrs. S.R. Leckey (Correspondence and Divorce Case) 1915 (Box 24)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: Deed of Henry Lee and wife to Thomas Lang 1912 Jul. 30 (Oversize Oversize)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: Fitzhugh Lee Estate 1905-1913, 2 folders (Box 24)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: New Jersey Iron Company of Virginia 1872-1876 (Box 25)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: Estate of Ruth Niece 1821-1850 (Box 25)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: Paris Universal Exposition 1878 (Box 25)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: Power of Attorney Appointment to Francis T. Anderson 1841 Dec. 9 (Oversize Oversize)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: Estate of Emma L. Pullam 1883-1891 (Box 25)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: Highway Construction in Rockbridge County 1918 (Box 25)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: Rockbridge Hotel 1893-1899 (Box 25)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: Shares of Great Southern Stove Company and Falls City Malleable Iron and Steel Works 1891, 1892 (Box 25)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: Statements of Cross Ties and Telephone Poles 1896-1901 (Box 25)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: Richmond and Alleghany Railroad Company 1881 (Box 25)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: Richmond and Alleghany Railroad Company 1882 (Box 26)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: Richmond and Alleghany Railroad Company - Land Acquisition 1881-1889 (Box 26)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: Court Cases Involving the Richmond, Fredericksburg and Potomac Railroad Company 1908-1910 (Box 26)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: The Tredegar Company 1840-1869, 5 folders (Box 26)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: The Tredegar Company 1870-1920, 4 folders (Box 27)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: University of Virginia Bachelor of Law diploma to William A. Anderson 1866 Jun. 29 (Oversize Oversize)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: Virginia Central Railroad Company Stock Sheet 1872 (Oversize Oversize)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: Virginia Lands 1783-1891, 4 folders (Box 27)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: Virginia Lands 1892-1912, 7 folders (Box 28)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: Virginia Lands 1913-1927, 8 folders (Box 29)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: Virginia Lands 1928-1929, n.d., 2 folders (Box 30)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: Virginia Lands - Anderson Lands in Botetourt, Bedford and Rockingham Counties 1771-1890, 2 folders (Box 30)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: Virginia Lands - Barbours Creek Tract 1854-1920, 4 folders (Box 30)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: Virginia Lands - Barbours Creek Tract 1920-1930, n.d., 6 folders (Box 31)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: Virginia Lands - Barbours Creek Tract Reports 1902 (Box 31)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: Virginia Lands - Glenwood Estate 1881-1919, n.d., 4 folders (Box 32)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: Virginia Lands - Grace Furnace Property 1907-1916, 2 folders (Box 32)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: Virginia Lands - Irish Creek Lands 1877-1913 (Box 32)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: Virginia Lands - Irish Creek Lands 1914-1917, n.d., 2 folders (Box 33)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: Virginia Lands - Plats and Maps ca. 1856-1912, n.d. (Oversize Oversize)
    including: Jim Beal grant; Glenwood Estate and Iron Property; Bailey's Mountain Tract; two surveys of John Barclay's land by J. M. Brockenbrough; land along Pott's Creek, Barber's Creek and Mill Creek by W.M. Echols; Plat of J.W. Gilmore land on James River by Sydney Vale; Unsold portions of Hoffman lands; Alum Spring Tract;Cove Tract, Irish Creek lands; map of lands in Craig and Roanoke Counties granted to William Fenwick (3 copies), Grace Property, and other miscellaneous lands
  - Legal and Financial Papers: Virginia Lands - Plats and Maps ca. 1866-1920 (Oversize Oversize)
    including: map of lands in Alleghany and Craig counties patented to William Fenwick; map showing Coal River Basin and Adjacent Territory between C & O and Norfolk & Western Railways, West Virginia; plat of Steele Survey; Map of Proposed "State Highway System" for Virginia; Reconnaissance map of Breckenridge Cove, Craig County, Virginia; lands on Irish Creek, in Rockbridge County, Virginia (Washington Campbell Tract); land plat showing the Fenwick Line; maps of land in Craig County, Virginia, on the waters of Barbours Creek, part of the William Fenwick grant and owned by W.A. Anderson and others, drawn by W.M. Echols
  - Legal and Financial Papers: Virginia - West Virginia Debt Controversy 1903-1911, 4 folders (Box 33)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: Virginia - West Virginia Debt Controversy 1911-1914, 8 folders (Box 34)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: Virginia - West Virginia Debt Controversy 1914-1915, 7 folders (Box 35)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: Virginia - West Virginia Debt Controversy 1916-1920, n.d., 8 folders (Box 36)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: Virginia - West Virginia Debt Controversy n.d. (Box 37)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: Virginia - West Virginia Debt Controversy - Court Transcripts 1909, 6 folders (Box 37)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: Virginia - West Virginia Debt Controversy - Court Transcripts 1909-1910, 4 folders (Box 38)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: Virginia - West Virginia Debt Controversy - Depositions 1920 (Box 39)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: Virginia - West Virginia Debt Controversy - Evidence 1920 (Box 39)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: Virginia - West Virginia Debt Controversy - Report of the Virginia Debt Commission to the General Assembly of Virginia 1921-1922 (Box 39)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: West Virginia Coal Lands, including J.G. Paxton Estate and Crescent Tract 1784-1893, 4 folders (Box 39)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: West Virginia Coal Lands, including J.G. Paxton Estate and Crescent Tract 1894-1900, 2 folders (Box 40)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: West Virginia Coal Lands - Maps and Plats 1884, n.d. (Oversize Oversize)
  - Legal and Financial Papers: West Virginia Coal Lands - Maps and Plats 1898 (Oversize Oversize)
  - Loyalty Oath of Francis T. Anderson 1865 Dec. 6 (Box 40)
  - Notes on McCorkle Family History 1913 (Box 40)
  - Wood Rainwater to R.C. Anderson, together with Anderson's Reply 1922 (Box 40)
  - "Invention of the McCormick Reaper" ca. 1910, 2 folders (Box 40)
  - Mural, "The Prophets" by John S. Sargent 1913 Dec. 7 (Box 40)
    in the Boston Public Library, published as an insert in The New York Times
  - Monthly Reports: Teachers of Nelson County 1914-1916 (Box 40)
  - Photographs: War Rally and Others 1917, n.d. (Box 40)
  - Material Relating to the Bronze Tablet at the Grave of William D. Washington 1848-1952 (Box 40)
  - Military Papers Pertaining to Dr. David S. Watson 1858-1861 (Box 40)
  - Miscellaneous Unmatched Envelopes 1780-1930, 4 folders (Box 41)
  - Miscellaneous Notebooks 1854-1898, 2 folders (Box 41)
- Series II: Anderson Ledgers
  - Bank Book, not indexed, 1871-1880 (Ledger, Volume 1, [032668349])
  - Bank Check Book, not indexed, 1898-1902 (Ledger, Volume 2, [032668350])
  - Cash Book, not indexed, 1891-1893 (Ledger, Volume 3, [032668351])
  - Day Book of Francis T. Anderson, not indexed, 1857 (Ledger, Volume 4, [032668346])
  - Day Book of Francis T. Anderson, not indexed, marked “Glenwood”, 1858-1861 (Ledger, Volume 5, [032668347])
  - Day Book of Francis T. Anderson, “Glenwood” not indexed, 1861 (Ledger, Volume 6, [032668348])
  - Journal Francis T. Anderson “Accounts Against Sundries”, 1830-1853 (Ledger, Volume 7, [032668363])
  - “Farm Journal” includes lists of enslaved persons in the back, 1857-1858 (Ledger, Volume 8, [032668372])
  - Journal “Anderson and Edmondson” with separate index enclosed, 1878-1884 (Ledger, Volume 9, [032668355])
  - Journal Glenwood Ferry records, 1858-1862 (Ledger, Volume 10, [032668325])
  - Journal Glenwood Ferry records, 1859-1861 (Ledger, Volume 11, [032668352])
  - Journal record of the “Rockbridge Company”, 1889-1893 (Ledger, Volume 12, [032668322])
  - Journal, chiefly an account of merchandise, with blacksmith’s work, and includes record of enslavers who hired out enslaved workers to the furnace (“Glenwood”), 1855-1858 (Ledger, Volume 13, [032668359])
  - Journal, a Record of the Rockbridge Soap Manufacturing Company, 1866-1870 (Ledger, Volume 14, [032668362])
  - Journal “Francis T. Anderson Account Book”, 1834-1843 (Ledger, Volume 15, [032668357])
  - Ledger of William A. Anderson, with an Inventory of his Estate, 1773-1811 (Ledger, Volume 16, [X032668360])
  - Ledger of William A. Anderson, “Bills Payable” and Notes Payable, 1840-1863 (Ledger, Volume 17, [X032668353])
  - Ledger of Francis T. Anderson, “Petty Ledger” (“Glenwood”), 1860-1862 (Ledger, Volume 18, [X032668358])
  - Ledger labeled “S and M” for sundries and merchandise, 1863-1869 (Ledger, Volume 19, [X032668373])
  - Ledger of William A. Anderson, “Private Ledger”, 1869-1902 (Ledger, Volume 20, [X032668364])
  - Ledger of William A. Anderson, with separate index enclosed, 1871-1900 (Ledger, Volume 21, [X032668368])
  - Ledger of the Rockbridge Company, bills receivable with dates due, includes separate index enclosed, 1890-1892 (Ledger, Volume 22, [X032668361])
  - Ledger, separate index enclosed, damaged, 1889-1891 (Ledger, Volume 23, [X032668369])
  - Ledger of the Rockbridge Company, 1889-1893 (Ledger, Volume 24, [X032668370])
  - Ledger of the Rockbridge Company, “Stock Ledger” separate index enclosed, 1889-1892 (Ledger, Volume 25, [X032668354])
  - Legal “Claim Book” of William A. Anderson, 1866-1894 (Ledger, Volume 26, [X032668356])
  - Letter Book of William A. Anderson, 1891 Oct-1892 Feb (Ledger, Volume 27, [X032668326])
  - Letter Book of William A. Anderson, 1892 Feb-Sept (Ledger, Volume 28, [X032668327])
  - Letter Book of William A. Anderson, 1892 Sep-1893 July (Ledger, Volume 29, [X032668341])
  - Letter Book of William A. Anderson, 1891 Apr-1902 Aug (Ledger, Volume 30, [X032668331])
  - Letter Book of William A. Anderson, 1894 Jan-Oct (Ledger, Volume 31, [X032668342])
  - Letter Book of William A. Anderson, 1894 Oct-1895 Feb (Ledger, Volume 32, [X032668332])
  - Letter Book of William A. Anderson, 1895 Nov-1896 July (Ledger, Volume 33, [X032668345])
  - Letter Book of William A. Anderson, 1896 July-1897 June (Ledger, Volume 34, [X032668333])
  - Letter Book of William A. Anderson, 1897 June-1898 July (Ledger, Volume 35, [X032668334])
  - Letter Book of William A. Anderson, 1898 July-1899 May (Ledger, Volume 36, [X032668335])
  - Letter Book of William A. Anderson, 1899 May-1900 Apr (Ledger, Volume 37, [X032668343])
  - Letter Book of William A. Anderson, 1900 Apr-1901 Apr (Ledger, Volume 38, [X032668336])
  - Letter Book of William A. Anderson (Personal), 1902 Jun-1903 Oct (Ledger, Volume 39, [X032668330])
  - Letter Book of William A. Anderson (Personal), 1903 Oct-1904 July (Ledger, Volume 40, [X032668340])
  - Letter Book of William A. Anderson (Personal), 1904 July-1905 May (Ledger, Volume 41, [X032668339])
  - Letter Book of William A. Anderson (Personal), 1906 Dec-1908 June (Ledger, Volume 42, [X032668338])
  - Letter Book of William A. Anderson (Personal), 1908 June-1910 Feb (Ledger, Volume 43, [X032668337])
  - Minute books Lexington Building Fund Association, 1854-1875 (Ledger, Volume 44, [X032668324])
  - Minute books the Directors of Blue Ridge Mineral Company, 1890-1893 (Ledger, Volume 45, [X032668323])
  - “Negro Book” indexed with accounts of labor done, supplies issued, etc. and the hires of enslaved persons, 1847-1849 (Ledger, Volume 46, [X032668374])
  - Subscription Book for Capital Stock in the Richmond & Louisville Railroad, Circa 1880 (Ledger, Volume 47, [X032668344])